Forget it.
忘了吧
Forget that you're told to never smile until you die.
忘了有人告诉你到死都别再笑的事情
I THINK THIS IS VERY WELL-WRITTEN.
（我认为这篇作文写得很好）
I'll do my best to come up with jokes.
我会努力想出笑话
We want to see you smile.
希望能够看到你的笑容
I found a pretty stone, big sis!
大姐 我找到一块美丽的石头
It looks pretty.
看起来很美
-Let's find more. -Okay.
-我们再找找看 -好喔
I found your stone, Mita.
我找到你的石头了 三田小姐
Please...
请你…
be our mommy.
当我们的妈妈吧
As you wish.
我知道了
What?
什么？
Mita really said that?
三田小姐真的这样说？
Wait a minute...
等一下
I can't do that!
我不可以这样做
Why not? Do you hate Mita?
为什么？你讨厌三田小姐吗？
That's not it, but...
不是这样 但是…
I was surprised, too.
我也觉得很意外
I never expected that she'd agree to be our mom.
我没有想过她会答应做我们的妈妈
But isn't this for the best?
可是这不是很好吗？
Mita will be with us forever now.
三田小姐以后都会跟我们在一起
-But still-- -I have returned.
-不过还是… -我回来了
-Welcome home! -Welcome home.
-欢迎回来！ -欢迎回来
I will prepare dinner now.
我现在去准备晚餐
Come on! Hurry up and propose.
来吧！快点跟她求婚
Give me a break.
放过我吧
Please, Daddy!
爸爸 求求你！
Excuse me, Mita.
不好意思 三田小姐
What is it?
有什么事吗？
Will you really be their mother?
你真的愿意做他们的妈妈？
If you don't mind, that is.
如果你不介意 我愿意
Wait.
等一下
But you know...
可是…
I was just thinking what our relationship will become.
我在想 那我们会是什么关系？
We're not going to become a married couple, are we?
难道我们要结婚吗？
I've already signed and placed my seal here.
我已经在上面签了名 盖了印章
What?
什么？
Wait a minute...
等一下…
Hold on. I can't do that.
等一下 我不能签
Why not?
为什么？
I mean, I'm the man who made their mother commit suicide!
我是害他们妈妈自杀的人
Ms. Asuda did not kill herself. It was an accident.
主人的太太并不是自杀 那只是意外
Oh. You're right, but...
你说得对 可是…
Besides, you have just started working at your new company,
再说 你刚刚在新公司上班
so your salary is lesser
所以薪水比较低
and should not be financially capable of hiring a housekeeper.
应该没有经济能力聘请家政妇
If I become a housewife,
如果我成为家庭主妇
it will reduce your financial burden
就可以减轻你的经济负担
and I will be able to take care of the children for the whole day.
而且我整天都可以照顾小孩
I believe this is the best solution.
我相信这是最好的办法
She's right, Dad!
爸爸 她说得对
Now you can focus on work without worrying about us!
那么你就可以专心工作 不用担心我们
I'll quit cram school
我不用再去补习班
and let Mita tutor me.
有三田小姐教我就可以了
Please, Daddy! I don't want Mita to be gone anymore!
爸爸 求求你 我不想让三田小姐再离开我们
One moment.
抱歉
Hey, Yui...
小结…
Do something about this, will you?
你说句话吧？
For now, just say that you'll take your time to think about the marriage.
现在你只要说 你需要时间考虑结婚的事
Mita can stay with us anyway.
反正三田小姐都会跟我们在一起
Isn't it fine, Dad?
爸爸 这不是很好吗？
Oh... Well, I guess you're right.
是的 你说得对
Mita.
三田小姐
Could you do that for us?
你愿意为了我们这样做吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
All right!
太好了
Mita.
三田小姐
Here you go.
给你的
Put your stone in here.
把你的石头放进去
As you wish.
我知道了
Then you don't need this stone now.
现在你不需要这块石头了
What? But that's Mommy.
为什么？这块石头是妈妈的
You do not need two mothers in this house.
一个家不需要两个妈妈
Everyone...
各位
I'm in your care from now on.
今后请你们多多指教
-Yui! -Yes?
-姐姐 -怎么了？
Have you told Santa what you want for Christmas?
你告诉圣诞老人 你想要什么圣诞礼物了吗？
-Oh, I'm still thinking about it. -What?
-我还没有想好 -什么？
Dinner is ready.
晚餐准备好了
-Okay. -All right!
-好的 -来啦！
-Hurry up and sit. -I'm so hungry.
-快点坐好 -我很饿
Huh? What's this?
奇怪 这是什么？
The food's really plain, compared to usual.
跟平时比起来 今天晚餐很清淡
Our financial circumstances aren't doing that well,
我们家的经济状况不是很好
Your father is raising you guys,
爸爸要赚钱养你们
so it's a given.
当然要吃好一点
Also, all of you can only eat two servings from now on.
还有从现在开始 你们每天只可以吃两餐
No way! That's not enough for me!
不是吧 这样我吃不饱
You don't have to do that, Mita...
三田小姐 你不用这样吧
I'm just saying that you do not have much savings left,
我想说 你的储蓄没有剩下多少
and you still have to pay off the loan for this house.
你还要付房贷
I believe that the kids should understand your circumstances.
我觉得应该让孩子们知道你的处境
Okay.
好的
Well... I guess we should just eat first.
那我们吃饭吧
-Thank you for the food.
-我开动了
Hey. What are you...
喂 你做什么…
From now on,
从现在开始
you will not be allowed to look at your phone while eating.
你们吃饭的时候 不可以看手机
What? But my entrance exams are coming soon.
为什么？可是我的入学考试快到了
If you can't solve a question as simple as that,
如果你连这么简单的问题也不会
I think you should give up on entering an private school.
我觉得你应该放弃考私校
It will help with our finances.
这样可以减轻家庭的经济负担
Hey, what is "family finances"?
什么是“家庭的经济”？
You will be in elementary school next year,
你明年就要上小学了
so stop acting spoiled and don't talk when you eat.
所以不要再撒娇了 还有吃饭时不要说话
Hey. You didn't have to be that harsh...
等一下 你不用这么严厉吧…
You're the eldest child,
你是长女
so you should help out with the household chores
所以应该帮忙做家务
-But Mita... -Mom.
-可是三田小姐… -叫“妈妈”
What?
什么？
I'm not Mita. Call me "Mom."
别叫我三田小姐 叫我“妈妈”
Please stop treating me like I'm your housekeeper.
别再把我当成你们的家政妇
Hey. What do you think, Dad?
爸爸 你觉得怎么样？
Don't you think she's acting weird?
你说 她是不是很奇怪？
Why don't you say something?
你说两句吧
Oh... Okay.
是 好的
Well, you're right.
你说得是
Mita. I...
三田小姐 我…
Huh? Wait, my stomach...
奇怪？等一下 我的肚子…
-Dad? -Dad!
-爸爸？ -爸爸
-Hey! -Are you all right?
-喂 -你怎么了？
It hurts...
好痛…
Let's call an ambulance!
快点叫救护车！
Dad! Are you all right? What's going on?
爸爸！你还好吗？怎么了？
You have stomach ulcers,
你有胃溃疡
and will need to be hospitalized for a week.
需要住院一星期
But how did this happen?
可是怎么会这样？
Weren't you feeling fine just a while ago, Dad?
爸爸 你之前不是好好的吗？
Well, yes.
是的
Please have a good rest. I will oversee everything at home.
请好好休息 我会打理家里的一切
Ms. Asuda?
阿须田太太？
His father-in-law is here to visit him.
岳父来看你先生了
Mita.
三田小姐
I'm sorry,
很抱歉
but could you not tell my father-in-law that you became their mother?
但是可以请你不要跟我岳父说 你当他们妈妈的事吗？
I'll tell him properly another time.
我之后找个时间再跟他说
As you wish.
我知道了
Hey. Are you all right?
你还好吗？
Oh... I'm sorry you had to come all the way here, Father-in-law.
爸 还麻烦你来一趟 真抱歉
Don't worry about it.
别这样说
I wanted to talk to you about something.
我有些事情要跟你说
What's the matter, Grandpa?
外公 是什么事情？
Well, actually...
其实是这样的…
It's about Urara.
是关于小丽的
She said she's going to marry the guy she met on the blind date.
她说要嫁给那个相亲认识的男人
She even decided on the wedding ceremony date without asking me.
她甚至没有问过我 就决定好婚期
What? So sudden?
什么？这么突然？
That fool asked me to keep it a secret from you guys,
那个傻瓜叫我不要让你们知道
and I raised my voice at her unknowingly.
我就忍不住说了她两句
What will you do, Father-in-law?
爸 那你要怎么做？
Maybe I'm just imagining things...
可能我想太多吧
But I think that...
但我觉得…
Urara's trying to give up on you.
小丽是想忘记你
Actually...
其实…
Urara told me something the other day.
之前小丽跟我讲过
I...
我…
I like you.
喜欢你
Sorry, but I'll never hand Urara over to you.
抱歉 但我永远 不会让小丽跟你在一起
Oh, of course.
那当然
I don't expect myself to marry someone else again, either.
我也不期望自己可以再跟别人结婚
So...
所以…
I just have no idea what I should do.
我真的不知道该怎么做
Shall I try to convince Ms. Urara?
不如让我劝一下小丽？
Really?
真的吗？
That's great!
太好了！
Maybe you might be able to do something!
小丽可能会听你劝
I'm counting on you, as it were!
这事就拜托你了
As you wish.
我知道了
We also have a few dresses which you can change into.
我们还有几件婚纱 你可以试试看
What's the matter, Mita?
三田小姐 怎么了？
Are you really planning to get married?
你真的打算结婚吗？
Yes. He is a really wonderful person.
是的 我的对象是一个很好的人
He doesn't mind that I'm a complete klutz,
他不介意我笨手笨脚
and it felt as if I've met my destined pair.
我觉得好像遇到了真命天子
But you don't look really happy about it.
不过你看起来并不快乐
I... I decided to stop smiling like a fool.
我…决定以后不要像个傻子那么爱笑
Just like you, Mita.
我要像你一样 三田小姐
He's getting transferred to New York for his work,
他将会被调派到纽约工作
so I think we'll really never meet again.
所以我们之后应该不会再见了
Please take care of Yui and the kids.
请好好照顾小结他们几个
Don't worry. I became their mother.
别担心 我已经当了他们的妈妈
What?
什么？
No way...
不是吧…
Then...
那么…
Are you going to marry Keiichi, Mita?
三田小姐 你会跟姐夫结婚吗？
Is there a problem with it?
你觉得有问题吗？
No, not really.
不 没有
If you're around,
如果你在他们身边
there's nothing to worry about.
就没有什么好担心了
Please...
请你…
be happy.
快乐起来
After climbing up this slope
爬上这座山丘之后
Sing with me, Mita.
三田小姐 跟我一起唱
You should call me "Mom."
你应该叫我“妈妈”
Oh... Sorry.
对不起
After climbing up
爬上这座
Forget the song that you sang with your dead mom.
别再唱死去的妈妈跟你一起唱的歌
What?
什么？
I'm home.
我回来了
What were you out doing so late?
你为什么这么晚才回来？
Oh, sorry. My laptop broke down,
对不起 我的电脑坏了
so I asked my friend to fix it.
所以去找朋友帮我修
Hurry up and have dinner, or I can't clean up.
快进来吃晚餐 不然我不能洗碗
-What's wrong, Kaito? -I stepped on a cockroach!
-海斗 怎么了？ -我踩到蟑螂了
I also left my phone in school. I can't believe this.
还有我居然把手机留在学校了
What?
什么？
And what's your problem?
你又怎么了？
I tried to give up my seat for an old lady on the train,
我在火车上想让座给婆婆
and she stomped her walking stick on my foot!
但她的拐杖戳到我的脚！
I ran off trying to endure the pain,
我忍着痛走开
and I fell off the stairs and fractured my ankle!
却从楼梯上摔下去 扭伤了脚踝
Just what are you doing?
你搞什么鬼？
-What's wrong Kii? -There's an insect in my milk!
-希衣 怎么啦？ -我的牛奶里面有小昆虫！
Just what's going on with everyone?
你们怎么啦？
You're all acting like Urara now.
你们现在跟小丽一模一样
Thanks.
谢谢
Stop playing around.
不要再玩了
Kakeru and Kaito, hurry up and study.
小翔和海斗 你们快点去念书
You need to bathe too, Kii.
希衣 你要去洗澡
-Okay. -Got it.
-好的 -知道了
Hey. You met Urara today, didn't you?
你今天去见小丽 对吧？
How did it go?
她还好吗？
She looked really happy.
她看起来很快乐
Her partner seems like a really nice person.
她的对象看起来是个好人
Then will Urara get married?
小丽会结婚吗？
Actually, why didn't you stop her?
但是为什么你不阻止她？
It can't be helped.
没办法
It's something Ms. Urara decided for herself.
这是小丽自己的决定
Forget about that.
别再说了
You should hurry up and eat.
快点吃晚餐
Tell me. What are you thinking?
告诉我 你在想些什么？
What do you mean?
你是什么意思？
You agreed to be our mom because you have something in mind, right?
你答应做我们的妈妈 到底有什么企图？
I am simply doing what any mother would do.
我只是做所有妈妈都会做的事
As the housewife of a family,
做一个家庭主妇
it is tough to educate the children,
并不容易 既要教养小孩
and think about the household finances.
又要管理家庭开支
I went along with your selfish whims when I was still your housekeeper,
我还是你们的家政妇时 可以容忍你们自私地闹脾气
but you should understand I can no longer do that once I become your mother.
可是我做了你们妈妈之后 当然不能继续这样
She really said that?
她真的这么说？
But you know...
可是…
I just can't accept it.
我真的无法接受
Why did Mita suddenly change so drastically?
为什么三田小姐突然性情大变？
What does "drastically" mean?
什么是“性情大变”？
Doesn't it feel like Mita became a completely different person, Kii?
希衣 你不觉得 三田小姐整个人都变了吗？
That reminds me.
听你这么说
Strange things have been happening recently.
我想到最近发生的一连串怪事
Did Dad get hospitalized because she put something inside his food?
爸爸住院 会不会是因为 她在他的食物里面放了什么东西？
Is she after Dad's insurance money?
她是不是贪图爸爸的保险金？
Wait, maybe she came to our family in the first place
等一下 可能她一开始来这里
to take over the household.
就想打我们家的主意
Stop it, both of you! Say something, Yui.
你们两个不要再说了！
Why are you guys...
你们几个…
sitting around here and talking in secret?
坐在这里说什么秘密？
Oh, no. It's nothing. Right?
我们没有 对吧？
Yeah.
对
Hurry up and go home.
快点回家
I need everyone to help me with something.
我需要你们帮我做一些事情
We will do spring cleaning now,
我们现在要进行大扫除
so I will throw away everything that's not needed.
我想扔掉所有没用的东西
First...
首先…
We start with this.
我们要扔掉这个
What?
-什么？
Kakeru and Kaito, the two of you will throw it away.
小翔和海斗 你们负责把它扔掉
-There's no way we can do that! -Right! It's Mom's altar.
-绝对不能扔掉！ -对啊！这是妈妈的祭坛
I am your mother.
我才是你们的妈妈
Kii.
希衣
Throw this away, too.
这个也要扔掉
No!
不要！
We don't want that, either.
那个也不能扔掉
Stop it! Why are you saying such things, Mita?
不要这样！ 三田小姐 为什么你会这么说？
If you won't do it,
如果你们不这么做
you don't need to stay in this house.
就不要留在这个家
Get out.
滚出去
What?
-什么？
If you won't listen to your mom, get out of this house.
如果你们不听妈妈说的话 就滚出去
Everyone...
我们…
Let's go.
一起走吧
Come with me, Kii.
希衣 跟我一起走
Mita really said that?
三田小姐真的这样说？
We can't take it anymore.
我们再也受不了了
Please, Dad.
拜托 爸爸 这样继续下去
Okay.
我知道了
Then let's call your grandfather.
我们去找你们外公吧
Wait, I can't.
等等 不行
What? Why?
什么？为什么？
Urara's getting married tomorrow, so he won't have time for this.
小丽明天结婚 他没有时间理我们
Say, Urara...
小丽…
Are you really fine with this?
你真的想嫁给他吗？
Dad...
爸
Thank you for everything you've done for me.
谢谢你一直以来的照顾
Just what are you saying, as it were?
你在说什么？真是的
It's almost time to enter the hall.
是时候进教堂了
Wait!
等一下！
What's wrong, everyone?
你们怎么来了？
Sorry to bother you at a time like this, Urara.
小丽 我们这个时候打扰你 很抱歉
The moment Mita became our mom,
自从三田小姐当了我们的妈妈
she's been really mean to us!
她一直对我们很严苛
What did you say?
你说什么？
The home got depressing, and we stopped smiling.
家里的人都不开心 我们脸上也没有了笑容
We tried hard to think about what we can do,
我们很努力去想 应该怎么做
but we just have no idea what to do!
可是真的想不出办法
And then, I was reminded of you, Urara.
然后我想到小丽
You always come visit us, and whenever we talked about our problems
你常常来我们家 当我们遇到问题
you would always say, "I'll do something about it!"
你总是说“我会想办法的”
I just kept thinking of it!
我一直想起你说的话
The bride is now entering the hall.
现在请新娘步入礼堂
What?
怎么回事
I'm truly sorry about this!
真的很抱歉！
Hey! What are you doing, Mita?
等一下 三田小姐 你在做什么？
You guys wouldn't listen, so I'm trying to burn this.
你们不听我说的话 所以我要把它烧了
Hey! Stop this!
喂 不要这样！
Why are you here?
你为什么在这里？
You were supposed to get married today.
今天应该是你结婚的日子
I heard that you were being mean to the kids!
我听说你对他们几个很严苛
What are you talking about?
你在说什么？
In the first place, you said you would never come to this house again.
首先 你说过不会再踏入这个家
That's...
那是…
What are you guys thinking about, bringing someone like her here?
你们在想什么？ 为什么把她这种人带回家？
As punishment, you will have no dinner.
作为惩罚 你们今天晚上没有饭吃
Also, let's just cancel the Christmas party.
还有圣诞派对也会取消
Wait...
等一下…
Why are you doing this, Mita?
三田小姐 你为什么要这样做？
An outsider should not interfere in our family matters.
我们的家事不需要外人插手
Stop saying such mean things!
说话不要那么刻薄
Urara came because she's worried about us!
小丽来这里是因为她担心我们
What are you saying?
你们在说什么？
You guys were the ones who said that nothing good ever happens
是你们自己说的
Chase her out right now,
快把她赶出去
and never let her in again.
别再让她踏入这个家
There's no way we can do that!
我们绝对不会这样做
Urara came over even though it's her wedding ceremony!
就算今天是小丽的婚礼 她还是来看我们
I've been thinking about it.
我在想
Bad things have been happening to us lately
最近我们发生一连串不幸的事情
because Urara stopped coming over.
是因为小丽不再来我们家
I realized it, too.
我也发现
Urara always pulled the old maid and stuff,
小丽总是对我们啰啰嗦嗦
because she was warding off all the bad luck and disaster for us!
是因为她想要为我们避开 所有不幸和灾难
I don't like it that I can never see Urara again!
我不想以后都见不到小丽
Then...
那么…
Me...
我…
Or that woman.
或是那个女人
Choose either one of us.
两个只能选一个
Who do you prefer having to protect you,
你们想哪一个来保护你们？
and who is the one you really need?
你们需要哪一个？
Wait a minute. I didn't come here to...
等一下 我来这里不是要…
Please keep quiet.
请你不要插嘴
This is...
这是…
something the children should decide
他们几个孩子要做的决定
We can't decide one or the other.
我们决定不了选哪一个
What should we do, Yui?
姐姐 我们应该怎么做？
I...
我…
No matter what happens to us,
不管我们发生什么事
Urara always cherishes us.
小丽总是很爱护我们
I believe that she will never betray us.
我相信她永远不会出卖我们
So...
所以…
Urara...
小丽…
I want you to be with us forever.
我想你以后都跟我们一起
Yui...
姐姐…
You...
你…
You are not our mother.
不是我们的妈妈
I understand.
我知道了
If so, I will leave the house.
这样的话 我会离开这个家
Wait, Mita!
等一下 三田小姐！
There's no point stopping me.
不用挽留我了
This is something you have decided.
这是你们自己的决定
Could it be that Mita...
难道三田小姐…
Urara?
小丽？
-Call Dad. -Got it.
-打给爸爸 -好的
Mita!
三田小姐！
Mita. You did all that on purpose, right?
三田小姐 你是故意这样做的吧？
You did all that
你做这一切
so that Yui and the kids will tell you to get out, right?
都是想让小结他们把你赶走 对吧？
Is it because you think you'll become happy
因为你觉得 如果继续跟他们在一起
if you continue to stay with them?
就会得到快乐 对吧？
So happy that you think you'll start to smile?
你怕自己脸上再有笑容 是吗？
Then isn't that all right?
那样有什么不好？
Yui and the kids need you more than someone like me--
跟我这样的人比起来 他们几个孩子更需要你…
Hey, what are you--
喂 你为什么…
Stop that!
停手！
If you don't stop, I'm going to get mad!
如果你不停手 我真的会生气！
Hey, what--
喂 你怎么…
Stop--
停手…
Hey--
喂…
Don't mess with me!
不要惹我生气！
Hey!
喂！
Just what's wrong with you?
你到底有什么问题？
Hey! What are the two of you doing?
喂！你们两个怎么啦？
Please get angry, just like that.
请你尽情生气 就像这样
What?
什么？
Please cry when you feel like crying.
如果想哭 就哭出来吧
Please stop trying to be considerate,
请你别再顾虑别人
and force yourself to smile.
不要再强颜欢笑
Please stop trying to please others,
请你别再满足别人
or do things just to make others happy.
或者只是为了别人高兴而做事
If you want to become their family, that is.
如果你想成为他们的家人 就承认吧
If you really wish to protect that family, that is.
如果你想保护他们一家 也都承认吧
But I...
可是我…
You...
你…
You might not be able to become Mr. Asuda's wife.
可能不会成为主人的太太
You might not be able to become the children's mother.
也可能不会成为他们小孩的妈妈
But you can become their guardian.
但是你可以成为他们的监护人
"I will do something about it."
“我会想办法”
"I hope you can grow to love instead of hating one another."
“我希望你们长大了懂得爱人 而不是互相讨厌”
"It will be fine. Just tell him how you really feel."
“别担心 对他说你真正的感受”
All the things you have said are correct.
你所说的事情都是正确的
However, you only conveyed them the wrong way.
只是表达的方式不对
From now on, don't just be nice to them.
从现在起 别只管对他们好
Please be harsh on them, too.
请你对他们严厉一点
Please keep pulling the old maid like you always have
请你继续像个老太婆一样念他们
and deflect all the misfortunes that may befall the family.
为他们一家挡开所有的不幸
And...
还有…
One last thing.
最后一件事
Please embrace everyone with that smile of yours.
请带着你的笑容 拥抱他们每一个人
You must never...
你永远也不要…
become someone like me.
成为像我这样的人
I got it.
我明白了
I...
我…
I will always live on...
会努力活下去…
without forgetting my smile.
不会忘记自己的笑容
Please excuse me.
我先告辞了
Wait, Mita!
等一下 三田小姐！
Could we have a proper farewell?
我们可以好好道别吗？
We don't want you to leave like this.
我们不想要你就这样离开
Right. It's Christmas eve tomorrow,
对了 明天就是平安夜
so could you at least stay with the kids until then?
所以请你留下来陪他们 至少过完明天再走 可以吗？
Please!
请你答应吧
Mita...
三田小姐…
I'm asking you, too.
我也请你留下来
As you wish.
我知道了
How did it go, Urara?
小丽 怎么样？
We cancelled the ceremony on the day itself, so there's no refunds.
我们当天才取消婚礼 所以不能退款
I see...
是喔
Then I'll pay you.
费用由我来付吧
The kids caused you trouble, and I need to take responsibility.
孩子们带给你麻烦 我都有责任
You really shouldn't worry about it, Keiichi!
姐夫 你真的不用这么做
I finally realized why I fell for a man that I shouldn't have fallen for.
我终于知道自己 为什么喜欢上不该喜欢的人
I like Yui and the kids.
我喜欢小结他们几个
I want to be with them, and I don't want to sever our relationship!
我想跟孩子们一起 而且我不想跟你分开！
Oh... I see.
是喔
Thanks, Urara.
谢谢你 小丽
He's here.
他来了
Excuse me. I'm really sorry about yesterday!
对不起 昨天的事真的很抱歉
I was throwing a fit because I didn't want to marry someone I don't love.
我很任性 因为我不想嫁给我不爱的人
It was too disrespectful to you.
这样对你太不尊重了
It's fine. I feel the same way, too.
没关系 我也这样觉得
What?
什么？
Actually, there's someone I'm going out with.
其实我有跟别人约会
She couldn't go against her father.
她不能违背她父亲的意愿
She's marrying a man that she met on a blind date.
要嫁给相亲认识的男人
It didn't sit right with me, either.
我也不想这样跟你结婚
I see! That's why you didn't mind me!
这样啊 所以你才不介意我这个样子
But...
可是…
After I saw what you've done...
我看见你这样做之后…
I've plucked up my courage.
我也鼓起勇气
I'm going to see her now.
我现在要去找她
What?
什么？
Stop this ceremony right now!
马上停止婚礼！
Sorry!
对不起！
Who the hell are you?
你到底是谁？
No way!
不是吧！
Let's go!
走吧！
Hold up!
等一下！
Natori?
名取？
Chief...
课长
Then that was the director's daughter?
那位新娘是董事长的千金？
Wait for me!
等等我！
It looks so tasty!
看起来很好吃！
-Wow! Apfelstrude? -All right.
-天啊！那是苹果卷吗？ -是的
-Let's go, it's chilly. -Tickle, tickle...
走吧 这里有点冷
What are you doing?
你在做什么？
I was wondering if you were going to smile.
我想逗你笑
I've never seen you smile before, Mita.
三田小姐 我从来没有看你笑过
Oh, right!
对了！
Dad. Don't you think we should ask Santa to give Mita a present, too?
爸爸 不如我们请圣诞老人 也送三田小姐一份礼物吧？
Oh, you're right! What do you want, Mita?
对了！三田小姐 你想要什么？
I don't need anything.
我不需要任何东西
Don't say that.
别这样说
Right. When is your birthday, Mita?
对了 三田小姐 你什么时候生日？
It's December 25.
12月25日
-What? -No way!
-什么？ -不是吧
Then we definitely should get something for you!
我们一定要送你礼物
What? Won't Santa give her a present?
什么？圣诞老人 不是会送礼物给她吗？
Please have one.
请拿一份看看
-Well... -That's...
-这个… -那是…
Please have one.
请拿一份看看
Kazama.
风间
What are you doing here?
你在这里做什么？
I thought you went back to the countryside.
我以为你回乡下了
I told my parents the reason I quit the company,
我告诉父母 我辞职的真正原因
and we got into a fight.
我们吵了起来
So I came back here again.
所以我又回来了
I see...
是这样啊
I'm sure this must be karma.
这一定是报应
Since I did something that made your wife commit suicide.
因为我所做的事令你太太自杀
Mom did not kill herself!
妈妈不是自杀的
It's an accident.
那是意外
this is the truth that we have decided on.
我们认为这就是事情的真相
So, please stop blaming yourself.
所以你不要再自责了
For you.
送给你
Mr. Asuda.
主人
What?
怎么了？
MOVING SERVICE
（搬家服务）
Excuse me.
等一下
What happened?
发生什么事了？
I asked my husband to give me back Tsubasa,
我请丈夫把小翼还给我
but it didn't work.
可是没有用
Just how am I supposed to live from now on?
我以后要怎么活下去？
You can't give up.
你不可以放弃
Even a scumbag of a father like me was able to take back my kids.
就算像我这样没用的父亲 也可以跟小孩修复关系
Tsubasa's mother can only be you in this entire world.
在这个世界上 只有你能够当小翼的妈妈
It's impossible. Not unless a miracle happens.
不可能的 除非有奇迹发生
What's a "miracle"?
什么是“奇迹”？
What? Well...
什么？这个嘛…
That's...
就是…
A miracle refers to something where
奇迹是指
It is something that happens when you have a strong willpower.
只有当你的意志够坚定 这些事情才会发生
It is called a miracle, simply because they do happen.
我们称之为“奇迹” 正是因为这些事情真的发生了
It will never happen to someone who has already given up on hope.
但奇迹绝对不会发生在 已经放弃希望的人身上
Mommy!
妈妈！
I'm sorry, Tsubasa.
小翼 对不起
No matter what happens,
无论发生什么事
I'll make sure that we can live together again.
我一定会努力 让我们再一起生活
Really?
真的吗？
It's a promise.
我答应你
-It's so beautiful. -Yes.
-真的很美 -是的
There's a lot of stars, too.
也有很多星星呢
Dad. Is that the Polaris?
爸爸 那是北极星吗？
Right.
是
What is a "Polaris"?
什么是“北极星”？
What? Well... How do I explain it?
什么？这个…怎么说呢？
The Polaris is...
北极星就是…
a star that always shines at the same location,
一颗有固定发光点的恒星
so when you are lost,
所以当你迷路的时候
you can find your way just by looking at it.
只要看着这颗星 就可以找到自己的方向
It is an important wayfinder.
这是很重要的坐标
What's a "wayfinder"?
什么是“坐标”？
You can ask Mita about that later.
之后再问三田小姐吧
Right, Mita?
三田小姐 是吗？
Dinner is ready.
晚餐准备好了
Wow.
天啊
It looks even more extravagant today!
今天的晚餐很丰盛
You're really good at this, Mita!
三田小姐 你的厨艺真好！
Yui helped me out today, too.
今天小结也有帮忙做饭
Really?
真的？
Is that true, Yui?
小结 真的吗？
Well, yes. Hurry up and eat.
是的 我们快点吃饭吧！
You have to join us today, Mita.
三田小姐 你今天跟我们一起吃饭吧
That's fine, right Mita?
三田小姐 可以吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
All right!
太好了！
Here you go.
来
Done.
给你
I'm so hungry that I'm going to die!
我快饿死了！
Jeez, Kakeru...
天啊 小翔…
Were you that hungry?
你饿成这个样子？
-That wasn't me! -What?
-不是我啊 -什么？
Wasn't it you, Dad?
爸爸 是你吧？
No! What are you saying?
不是 你说什么啊？
-Then who was it? -It wasn't me.
-那是谁？ -不是我
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
That was me.
是我
No way!
不是吧！
Mita!
三田小姐
Well, I guess we should dig in first.
我们吃饭吧
Okay. Thank you for the food!
好的 我开动了
-Thank you for the food!
-我开动了！
Oh, right.
对了
We really want to give you a present, Mita.
三田小姐 我们很想送你一份礼物
Is there anything you want?
你有没有什么想要的？
Doesn't Santa give us presents instead?
圣诞老人不是会送我们礼物吗？
Well, it's because Mita's birthday is tomorrow.
因为明天是三田小姐的生日
It's a birthday present.
这是一份生日礼物
We've thought about it, but we just don't know what you would like.
我们想过了 但是不知道你喜欢什么
I just want one thing.
我只想要一件东西
What?
是什么？
What is it?
你想要什么？
Kii.
希衣
Could you give me my stone?
你可以把我那颗石头送我吗？
What?
什么？
No!
不要！
Hey, Kii.
喂 希衣
I...
我…
I really don't want Mita to go!
真的不想三田小姐离开我们！
Don't cry, Kii.
希衣 不要哭
Come on. You can't cry, Kii.
来吧 希衣 你不能哭
Mita.
三田小姐
Could you please stay with us, at least for Kii?
你可以留下来跟我们在一起吗？ 就当是为了希衣
If you're worried that we can't afford it,
如果你担心我们请不起你
I'll go work part-time or something!
我会去找兼职
I'm sorry...
对不起…
but Ms. Harumi has set up a new housekeeping agency in Okinawa,
可是晴海所长已经 在冲绳开了新的家政妇介绍所
and I will be departing tomorrow.
我明天就要离开这里了
-What?
-什么？
No way.
不是吧？
We still haven't seen you smile, Mita.
三田小姐 我们还没有看见你的笑容
Thanks to you, I had the courage to continue living.
是因为你 我才有勇气活下去
I wanted to repay you for everything you've done!
我想报答你为我们做的一切
Your thought is more than enough.
我知道你这份心意就够了
Thanks to everyone,
多亏你们大家
I found light in my life, even though it's just a small glimmer of it.
我才找到生命的曙光 虽然只有一丝的光芒
However...
可是…
My feelings towards my late husband and son
我对死去丈夫和儿子的感情
will never disappear.
永远都不会消失
I have no choice but to bear the sin of letting the both of them die.
我没有办法不为他们的死背负罪责
But from now on...
但是从现在开始…
I found light in my life, thanks to everyone.
因为你们 我找到生命的曙光
I would like to rely on that faint light and continue working as a housekeeper.
我想借着这份微弱的光芒 继续从事家政妇这份工作
With my own will.
按自己的心意行事
I understand.
我明白了
If you insist on quitting...
如果你坚持要离开…
Then I have one last order for you.
我有一个最后的命令
Mita.
三田小姐
What is it?
是什么？
Please smile.
请你笑吧
Right now...
现在…
you might think that you shouldn't smile because of your late husband and son.
因为你死去的丈夫和儿子 你可能觉得自己不应该笑
But do you think that's what they would have wanted?
但你觉得他们会想要你变成这样吗？
You're still alive.
你仍然活着
You can still feel hunger, like just now.
你仍然会饿 像刚才那样
You also can feel the cold.
你也会感到冷
Your finger bled when you cut yourself.
如果割伤了手指 你会流血
You got mad at the kids.
你会对小孩生气
You cried at the amusement park.
你在游乐场会哭
You're not a robot, but a human! So...
你不是机器人 而是一个人 所以…
For our sake... No.
为了我们…
For your late husband and son...
为了你死去的丈夫和儿子…
I want you to smile for their sake.
我想要你为了他们而笑
How could you leave without letting us see you smile?
我们还没看见你笑 你怎么可以就这样离开？
It's cowardly!
这样很懦弱
I won't accept it!
我不许你这样
Please smile, Mita.
请你笑吧 三田小姐
As you wish.
我知道了
Mita.
三田小姐
Promise me.
答应我
No matter which family you go to from now on,
不管你以后到哪一家工作
you must always act on your own will.
都一定要按自己的心意行事
As you wish.
我知道了
Don't you ever promise that you'll do anything they ask,
千万别对他们有求必应
and try anything dangerous
或是做危险的事情
like what you did here, okay?
就像你在我们家那样 知道吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
I...
我…
If I ever feel like eating your cooking,
如果我想再吃你做的菜
can I go visit you?
可以去找你吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
If...
如果…
If I enter a private school and make lots of friends,
如果我考进私校 交了很多朋友
you have to celebrate it for me, okay?
你要为我庆祝 可以吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
I'm going to become strong.
我会变得坚强
I'll become a strong person who will protect everyone!
我会成为一个坚强的人 保护所有人！
So you have to come see us again, okay?
所以你一定要回来看我们 可以吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
All of us cannot be thankful enough for what you did for us.
你为我们所做的一切 我们都感激不尽
You saved all of us, Mita.
三田小姐 是你救了我们
So if you're ever in trouble,
所以如果以后你遇到麻烦
you can rely on us, okay?
我们也会帮你解决 可以吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
If...
如果…
If you ever call me,
如果你打给我
I'll be the first to be there for you, no matter what it may be.
无论发生什么事 我都会第一个去找你
As you wish.
我知道了
If you come across a difficult question,
如果你遇到任何难题
I'll definitely solve it for you!
我一定会帮你解决！
As you wish.
我知道了
Mita.
三田小姐
Thank you for everything.
谢谢你为我们做的一切
Thanks to you, I was able to get back my family.
因为有你 我才能够 修补跟家人的关系
Please stop blaming yourself anymore.
请你不要再自责了
This time, it's your turn to become happy.
这次 轮到你要快乐起来了
If you don't become happy, I won't forgive you.
如果你不快乐 我不会放过你的
As you wish.
我知道了
From now on...
从现在开始…
You have to laugh lots and lots, okay?
你要尽情欢笑 知道吗？
Mita.
三田小姐
As you wish.
我知道了
Let's eat, okay?
我们吃饭吧？
You too, Mita.
三田小姐 你也是
HARUMI HOUSEKEEPING AGENCY WE HAVE RELOCATED DUE TO PERSONAL REASONS
（晴海家政妇介绍所 因私人理由已迁移新址）
Sorry about this, Akari.
灯子 不好意思
You had to help me out with all these.
辛苦你帮我搬东西
No problem.
没问题
Oh, isn't it almost time?
天啊 时间差不多了吧？
You promised to say goodbye to them, right?
你答应跟他们道别 对吧？
Hurry up.
快点去吧
Thank you.
谢谢你
What is it?
怎么了？
Akari...
灯子…
Could you...
你可不可以…
do that for me, too?
也为我破例一次？
What are you referring to?
你指的是什么？
Could you smile for me?
你可以为我笑一下吗？
Never mind.
没关系
I'll wait for the day you can smile naturally.
我会等哪一天你可以自然地笑
But still, Akari...
但是灯子…
You...
你啊…
I'm just so happy for you.
我真的替你高兴
I'm so happy for you.
太好了
After climbing up
爬上这座
This slope
山丘之后
There's a tree
往右边走
to the right
有一棵树
When you turn at the tree
在树的地方转弯
and walk straight
然后继续前进
Your beloved home is there waiting for you
你可爱的家在等着你
BUS STOP
（公交车站）
I'm sorry. Kii was the one who suggested we have our final farewell here.
抱歉 本来是希衣提议说 我们来这里跟你道别
She said that she's sick, but I'm sure she's just feigning it.
她说自己不舒服 可是我敢说她是装病的
Right?
对吧？
Yeah.
对
Oh, it's here.
车来了
Oh, my! I'm really sorry about this, everyone.
唉唷 各位真的很抱歉
It's all because I suddenly decided to relocate to Okinawa.
都怪我突然决定要搬到冲绳
Oh, by the way. This isn't an aloha shirt, but a kariyushi shirt.
对了 这不是夏威夷衬衫喔 而是冲绳花衬衫
Okay. Let's go, Akari.
灯子 我们走吧
Please excuse me.
我告辞了
Maybe Mita was Santa Claus.
三田小姐可能是圣诞老人
Huh? What are you talking about?
什么？你在说什么？
I mean, her birthday's on December 25.
我是说 她的生日是在12月25日
Her name "Mita" could also be read as "Santa."
她的名字“三田小姐” 读起来也跟“圣诞”很像
What?
什么？
San... ta?
圣…诞？
No way...
不是吧？
Akari. Are you really fine with this?
灯子 你真的觉得这样好吗？
I'm just relocating the shop into the city,
我只是把事务所搬到市中心
since that building was getting old.
因为之前那幢大厦太旧了
It's fine.
这样就好了
Mita!
三田小姐！
What's going on?
怎么啦？
My stomach hurts! Hey!
我肚子痛 等一下
Please stop, driver! Stop!
司机 请停下来 停车！
You can drive off now, driver! I feel better!
司机 可以开车了 我没事了
Here you go.
这个送你
Thank you very much.
谢谢你
There is something I would like to give you too.
我也有东西送给你
"I LOVE YOU, KII."
（希衣 我爱你）
You should let go now, Kii.
希衣 好了啦
Okay.
是
Thank you for everything.
感谢你们为我所做的一切
Everyone, I called Grandpa over for a sukiyaki party today!
我今天请你们的外公一起来吃寿喜烧
All right!
太好了！
Kii. Could you teach me the song Mommy sang?
希衣 你可以教我唱 你妈妈常常唱的那首歌吗？
Sure.
当然可以
When you turn at the tree
在树的地方转弯
and walk straight
然后继续前进
Your beloved home is there waiting for you
你可爱的家在等着你
That's our Polaris.
那里就是我们的北极星
Yes.
是的
No matter what happens,
无论发生什么事
we just need to look at where it is and come home.
我们只要朝着这个方向 就能回家
Hey, everyone!
嗨 你们回来了！
I bought some great beef, as it were!
我买了很棒的牛肉！
All right! Great beef!
太棒了！有牛肉吃！
-Let's go! -All right, as it were!
-来吧！ -好的！
I am here on behalf of Harumi Housekeeping Agency.
我来自晴海家政妇介绍所
I'm Mita, your housekeeper.
我是三田 您的家政妇
THE END
（剧终）
Subtitle translation by: Qianni Lu
字幕翻译：吴敬美